בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is at the bottom of
י"ז עמוד א', Yud Zayin Amud Aleph, and we're into a discussion
here about burying the dead and the משנה Mishna was on the
exemption of קריאת שמע. Krias Shema. The גמרא Gemara has now entered
a whole discussion about issues about the dead and what they're aware
of and what they're not aware of. Before we do, let me
just say one or two words related to summing up some of
the points before, which is the exemption of the משנה Mishna about
somebody who is an אונן, onain, somebody who has just experienced an
immediate loss and they're not yet given burial. There's a major debate
of the ראשונים Rishonim about it, which we should just take out
a second to mention.
רש"י Rashi says the exemption is עוסק במצוה. osek b'mitzvah. At least
he seems to be saying that. The first רש"י Rashi on מי
שמתו Mi she-meiso says
because he is distracted with concerns about the burial of the dead
and it's similar to the bridegroom. Which again raises the issues we
have by the bridegroom as to how much is it about distraction
and how much is it about עוסק במצוה. osek b'mitzvah. But nevertheless,
רש"י Rashi tries to put it into that class category. תוספות, Tosfos,
quoting the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, says that no, it's not exactly that. It
is an issue about כבוד המת, kavod hamet, that it would not
be considered respectful to the dead to be turning your interests to
other things. And one of the major debates between רש"י Rashi and
תוספות Tosfos has to do, for example, about all these גמרות Gemaras
that say that you don't דאוון daven and you don't make certain
ברכות berachos and so on, and all these things you don't do.
And if you look at the רש"י Rashi at the bottom of
י"ז עמוד א', Yud Zayin Amud Aleph, רש"י Rashi says that אינו
מברך, eino mivarech, אינו צריך לברך eino tzarich l'varech ברכת המזון, Birkas
Hamazon, and אינו מזמן, eino mizzamen, אינו צריך לברך eino tzarich l'varech
המוציא Hamotzi ולברך ul'varech ברכת המזון. Birkas Hamazon.
You're not required. But actually you have the option to do it.
And really it raises the obvious question: what do you mean עוסק
במצוה? osek b'mitzvah? Since when do we say that by an עוסק
במצוה osek b'mitzvah I don't have to make a ברכה beracha before
I eat bread or I don't have to make a ברכה beracha
after I eat? I mean the exemption here is so thoroughgoing: I
don't do any דאוונינג, davening, I don't do anything, right? We never
find that by a normal עוסק במצוה. osek b'mitzvah. So רש"י Rashi
tries to resolve that question by saying you're not required to; maybe
it is an option to be like other places; maybe here there's
also an issue of being distracted. But really you have the choice,
and if you want to make a ברכה beracha at the beginning,
you want to make a ברכה beracha at the end, all of
those things are options, because it is extreme the amount in which
you are exempted from all these things, and we never find it
elsewhere, and רש"י Rashi is just to say, okay, it's an option
to have. תוספות Tosfos says, and the way we rule is like
תוספות, Tosfos, that you don't have an option. You are actually forbidden
to make these ברכות berachos beginning and end because it's not just
an issue about עוסק במצוה, osek b'mitzvah, this is an issue that
to turn your attention to anything is to show you are turning
away from your focus on the מת, met, and therefore it would
be inappropriate, and therefore that's why it's not limited, it's more thoroughgoing
than עוסק במצוה, osek b'mitzvah, and therefore why it's actually forbidden and
not just to do these types of things. And תוספות Tosfos is
really the approach that we have. Now I'll just say one other
thing about תוספות, Tosfos, which is that it's not just עוסק במצוה,
osek b'mitzvah, I mean it's not just כבוד המת, kavod hamet, because
it's still a little funny. What exactly is the כבוד המת kavod
hamet that I can't go ahead and make a ברכה, beracha, especially
as the גמרא Gemara says I'm in another room, I have to
be eating anyway, but it's not like the מת met is literally
in front of me, even if it's just my obligation. So where
exactly is the כבוד kavod issue to be making a ברכה beracha
before I'm eating? So Rav Soloveitchik had beautifully explained this, that the
issue is not so much about turning your attention to something else
in terms of that's disrespectful from focusing on the מת, met, but
it's really a question about a sort of acknowledgment of
an assertion about what is or should be the psychological religious mindset
of somebody who has just experienced an immediate loss. And
because he says that basically observing מצוות mitzvos is an assertion of
meaning of life. Engagement in מצוות mitzvos means there's a purpose to
what we do, right? That you're saying that life is purposeful and
we're doing things to serve God and ultimately there's meaning and so
on. And that's what the engagement in מצוות mitzvos is about—a conscious
engagement in מצוות, mitzvos, not you have to do something, it happens
to be a מצוה. mitzvah. But the conscious engagement in מצוות mitzvos
is a statement about meaning of life. And he says that actually
this is a state where somebody has experienced an immediate loss and
maybe is questioning: questioning God's justice, questioning the meaning of life, questioning
how anything really makes sense. And that it would actually be inappropriate
to ask that person at that moment to do things that are
life-affirming.
And actually we allow a person to and maybe even require a
person to be in that state of existential questioning or shock and
don't demand a move into a more life-affirming action until after the
burial, where there can then be a type of a transition and
a moving back towards it. Even right after the burial, there's a
period where you're exempt from תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, you don't put
on תפילין, tefillin, but still that begins then the move back to
a more life-affirming type of a mode. So I think that that
really is a beautiful approach that Rav Soloveitchik has and it goes
to the fact that we're dealing with... here with more than just
simple עוסק במצוה. osek b'mitzvah.
Let me say one other thing about, two other things about this
again before we continue going further in the גמרא Gemara today. One
is the question about who is considered מת מוטל לפניו. met mutal
lefanav. The גמרא Gemara says it doesn't have to be literally מוטל
לפניו mutal lefanav as long as it's מוטל לקוברו. mutal lekovro. So
תוספות Tosafot asks, well what does מוטל לקוברו mutal lekovro mean? What
if you're at a different town, a different city, and somebody, and
somebody else, where the מת met is, another relative is handling all
the burial arrangements? Is that considered מוטל לקוברו? mutal lekovro? And it
tells the story that רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, when רבינו תם'ס Rabbeinu
Tam's sister died and רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam was in a different
city, רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam did not treat himself as an אונן
onen because he said my sister is married, her husband is taking
care of her burial arrangements, and therefore I'm not an אונן. onen.
Now, תוספות, Tosafot, that might be limited and תוספות Tosafot also gets
into other interesting questions about if somebody is, this happened as we
know in the time of the בעלי התוספות, Ba'alei haTosafot, people died
in prisons, the
מהר"ם מרוטנבורג Maharam mi-Rothenburg famously was taken as a prisoner to ransom
to the Jewish community and for an obscene amount of money, and
then after he died in prison and they were trying to sort
of get his body out of prison and so on, at what
stage does it consider to be מוטל לקוברו mutal lekovro if there
isn't that option to be קובר kover the person? The body's there
but you don't have any access to it. And תוספות Tosafot raises
those types of questions at what stage would a person be considered
an אונן onen when it's not their immediate responsibility or they don't
have access. So we generally rule that again because of this, it's
less of עוסק במצוה osek b'mitzvah and more about the state of
mind that the person is in, we generally rule a very broad
definition of מוטל לקוברו. mutal lekovro. The times we might make exceptions
is if a person is both out of town or out of
state, out of country, and not going to be flying in for
the funeral, and somebody else is taking care of it. That that
type of a mode would really put that person in a different
state altogether. But even if somebody is, it often happens, is flying
in and somebody else is there in the place where the person
has died and taking care of the arrangements, since this person who's
flying in is going to be involved in the funeral and is
coming in, that they're considered an אונן onen as well. But again,
raising very important practical questions of how to define that. One last
thing and then I'll take questions and then we'll move forward is
the גמרא'ס Gemara's point about the debate of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
and about an אונן onen and being whether on שבת Shabbat an
אונן onen does all the מצוות, mitzvot, and there's a debate of
whether the issue here about תשמיש המטה, tashmish hamita, whether sex is
permitted for the אונן onen or obligated to the אונן onen on
שבת. Shabbat. Now the
very, besides that question, the very fact that it suggests that sex
is normally forbidden for an אונן onen is itself surprising because we've
never seen that. What we've seen an אונן onen can't do is
do מצוות, mitzvot,
we haven't seen that he can't, for example, eat meat and drink
wine, we've never seen that he can't have sex. And that issue
leads to a whole debate of ראשונים, Rishonim, that there are
a number of ראשונים Rishonim that think that an אונן onen and
אבילות aveilut are somewhat similar and somewhat a continuation one state of
the other, and the reason an אונן onen can't have sex is
because an אבל avel can't have sex, and therefore apply that to
say that almost most of the laws that apply to an אבל
avel apply to an אונן onen as well in terms of bathing
and in terms of doing laundry and all these types of things
which we never have mentioned by an אונן. onen. And many, many
ראשונים Rishonim disagree, the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch does not mention other
laws that apply to an אונן onen other than this issue of
sex, but the רמ"א Rema does say, does put it in. And
I've actually have asked some people what they've been advised when they
have suffered losses, does the rabbi tell them oh you should know
you can't do this and you can't do this and goes through
the whole list of what an אבל avel can't do? And most
people tell me they never hear that from the rabbi. So it's
actually
interesting that there's a רמ"א Rema that says that you're supposed to
have most of the laws אבילות aveilut apply, but it's not in
the גמרא Gemara and it's interesting that I don't think that that
gets largely, that doesn't get communicated. Say רבינו תם'ס Rabbeinu Tam's sister,
if it had been his brother who died?
Right. So that's a very good question. It's possible the reason the
case is specifically about a sister with a husband is because the
model, one of the models of אבילות aveilut is the כהן, Kohen,
and the כהן Kohen only becomes טמא tamei when it's אחותו הבתולה
אשר לא היתה לאיש, achoto ha-betulah asher lo haytah l'ish, and it
could be the understanding that a person who is married, it's not
just that there happens to be another person, but the prime person
responsible
is the husband. I don't know if it would be the reverse,
what would be the reverse if it was the wife because of
certain assumptions there. But if it was like one brother was in
the city and another brother was away, it might not have been
the same assertion. It might be that there was an assumption that
there הלכתית halachically the prime responsible person was the husband and not
the other siblings.
So we don't know?
And we don't know, right, we don't know, right.
Because the familial relationship is the same whether she's married or not
married. Right. It's still his sister.
Right, absolutely. But it could be. It could be a practical question
who was taking care of the burial arrangements, and it could be
a הלכתי halachic question, an assumption that a spouse has more of
the primary responsibility than other than other relatives. But תוספות Tosafot does
not elaborate on that. And in general we don't rule that way
until, except with the combination of factors that I mentioned. So that
was a little summary of some of the הלכתי halachic issues from
yesterday and now we turn into what will be today's דף, daf,
which will be not so much הלכות, halachos, but a very, very
interesting departure from all of that. So let's resume from the bottom
of יח עמוד א, Yod-Chet Amud Aleph, about eight lines from the
bottom. רבי חייא ורבי יונתן הוו שקלי ואזלי בבית הקברות. Rabbi Chiyya
ve-Rabbi Yonatan havhu shakli ve-azli be-veit ha-kvarot. Rabbi Chiyya and Rabbi Yonatan
were going in a cemetery. הוה קשדיא תכלתא דרבי יונתן. Hava kashadya
tcheilta de-Rabbi Yonatan. So Rabbi Yonatan's ציצית, tzitzis, literally תכלת, tcheiles, the
blue, which is sometimes how the גמרא Gemara refers to ציצית, tzitzis,
was hanging out of his clothes. אמר ליה רבי חייא, Amar lei
Rabbi Chiyya, so Rabbi Chiyya said to him: דליי, Dalyey, lift them
up, tuck them in, כדי שלא יאמרו למחר באים אצלנו ועכשיו מחרפים
אותנו. kedei shelo yomru lemachar ba'im etzleinu ve-achshav mecharfim otanu.
Tomorrow they are going to be coming to us, people will be
dying, and now they're mocking us. Yeah, they think they're so great,
they're alive, they're doing this מצוה, mitzvah, and tomorrow they'll just be
coming to us, which is not something you want the dead to
be saying.
So now, by the way, I should say I translated this in
the modern idiom, which is tuck them
in, but actually their ציצית, tzitzis, they would wear outer garments and
cloaks and the ציצית tzitzis would be at the edges and they
probably more literally was that they were dragging on the ground, so
they were dragging over the graves. It's much more that sense of
mocking seen that way. And he says lift them up, they shouldn't
be dragging over the graves. Okay. So the גמרא, Gemara, so he
says back to him: אמר ליה ומי ידעי כולי האי, Amar lei
u-mi yad'ei kulei hai, do they know so much? והא כתיב והמתים
אינם יודעים מאומה, Ve-ha ktiv ve-ha-metim einam yod'im me'umah, and the פסוק
pasuk says the dead don't know at all anything. So אמר ליה,
amar lei, he said back to him: אם קרית לא שנית, Im
karita lo shanita, if you've learned תורה Torah then you have not
repeated it again so that you should really know it well. ואם
שנית לא שלשת, Ve-im shanita lo shilashta, and if you did it
twice you didn't do it three times. ואם שלשת לא פירשו לך,
Ve-im shilashta lo pirshu lach, if you did it three times and
you still didn't get the message, somebody wasn't explaining it to you.
Because here's what the פסוק pasuk says: כי החיים יודעים שימותו, Ki
ha-chayyim yod'im she-yamutu, the live know that they will die. And it
says והמתים אינם יודעים מאומה, ve-ha-metim einam yod'im me'umah, and the dead
know nothing. So what does this really mean? It means the following.
What does it mean the live know that they will die? אלו
צדיקים, Elu tzaddikim, these are the righteous, שבמיתתן נקראו חיים, she-ve-mitatan nikre'u
chayyim, that even in their death they're called alive. שנאמר ובניהו בן
יהוידע בן איש חי, Shene'emar u-Vnayahu ben Yehoyada ben ish chai, and
בניהו בן יהוידע Bnayahu ben Yehoyada the son of a living man,
which is, right, so that's what... what do you mean son of
a living man? So we'll see, רב פעלים מקבצאל, rav pe'alim mi-Kabtze'el,
of great, of great deeds from מקבצאל. Kabtze'el. הוא הכה את שני
אריאל מואב. Hu hikka es shnei Ariel Moav. He smote the two
lions or the two אריאל, Ariel, we'll see how the גמרא Gemara
interprets it, of מואב. Moav. והוא ירד והכה את הארי בתוך הבור
ביום השלג. Ve-hu yarad ve-hikka es ha-ari be-toch ha-bor be-yom ha-sheleg. And
he went down and smote the lion in the pit on the
day of the snow. But what does this whole פסוק pasuk mean?
It means the following.
בן איש חי, Ben ish chai, a son of a living man.
אטו כולי עלמא בני מיתי נינהו, Atu kulei alma bnei meiti ninhu,
so what does it mean? Well, everybody else is son of dead
people? אלא בן איש חי, Ella ben ish chai, so this is
where we learn it. שאפילו במיתתו קרוי חי. She-afillu be-mitato karui chai.
Somebody who even when he's died is still considered alive, which is
the righteous people, that even in their death they're still alive because
of the eternal life. So by the way, so how does the
end of the פסוק pasuk mean? והמתים אינם יודעים מאומה. ve-ha-metim einam
yod'im me'umah. כי החיים יודעים שימותו? Ki ha-chayyim yod'im she-yamutu? So the
interpret is: righteous people, which will always be alive, they are, and
it's so like ironic, they're always aware that they will physically die
and therefore they're always doing right deeds because the day of death
is always in front of them. Okay, but they are of eternal
life. So that's בן איש חי. Ben ish chai. So now says
רב פעלים מקבצאל, Rav pe'alim mi-Kabtze'el, what does this mean?
שריבה וקיבץ פועלים לתורה, She-ribba ve-kibbetz po'alim la-Torah, that he gathered, from
מקבצאל, Kabtze'el, קיבץ, kibbetz, he gathered many numerous people for the learning
of תורה, Torah, workers literally for תורה. Torah. והוא הכה את שני
אריאל מואב, Hu hikka es shnei Ariel Moav, שלא הניח כמותו, shelo
hiniach kemoto, he left nobody like him in terms of his achievements
of תורה, Torah, לא במקדש ראשון ולא במקדש שני, lo be-Mikdash Rishon
ve-lo be-Mikdash Sheni, not in the first בית המקדש Beit ha-Mikdash and
not in the second בית המקדש. Beit ha-Mikdash. Because אריאל Ariel is
often a word used to refer to the to the altar or
to the בית המקדש, Beit ha-Mikdash, particularly in יחזקאל Yechezkel it uses
that word. I think רש"י Rashi also mentions here about דוד. David.
Oh אריאל מואב, Ariel Moav, right, רש"י Rashi mentions also that an
association with מואב Moav is with דוד David who comes from רות
המואביה. Rut ha-Moaviyah. So he left no...
so where were we? והוא ירד והכה את הארי בתוך הבור ביום
השלג. Ve-hu yarad ve-hikka es ha-ari be-toch ha-bor be-yom ha-sheleg. He smote
the lion in the pit on the day of the snow. איכא
דאמרי דתבר גזיזי דברדא ונחת וטבל. Ika de-amrei de-tavar gezizei de-varda ve-nachat
ve-taval. So this is how פרום frum he was. One explanation is
that he broke the flows of ice, the chunks of ice, that
was the יום השלג yom ha-sheleg and he went down into the
pit, he went into the מקוה mikvah for his own to be
טובל, tovel, he broke through the ice in order to go in
the freezing waters of the מקוה. mikvah. Normally there are those stories
about righteous,
righteous women in Russia or whatever that would go to the מקוה
mikvah and they would really in snow and freezing waters and break
the ice in order to go. of the מקווה. Mikvah. So here
the גמרא Gemara is attributing this to him. איכא
דאמרי Ika Damri and others say דתנא ספרא דבי רב ביומא דסיתוא.
De Tana Sifra Devei Rav BYoma De Sitva. We learned about ספרא
דבי רב Sifra Devei Rav a while ago. Literally the books of
the house of רב, Rav, but this is the Tannaitic, thank you,
work on the book of ויקרא Vayikra and it's called we call
it the ספרא. Sifra. It was edited by רב Rav and these
are considered to be like the hardest Tannaitic works to, as we
just got through in the דף Daf learning all of the stuff
on קדשים. Kodshin. So the Tannaitic derivations of the פסוקים Pesukim in
ויקרא Vayikra about קדשים Kodshin are very difficult. So that's like breaking
ice. That's considered to be extremely difficult. Why exactly we connect it
to יום השלג, Yom Hasheleg, not exactly clear. But anyway, and then
it says like
this. What is it? On the day in the winter. והמתים אינם
יודעים מאומה. Vehametim Einam Yodim Meumah. Now back to the פסוק Posuk
you were quoting to me. The dead don't know. You took it
literally. Ha! That's not what it means. Here's what it means. The
dead don't know anything. והמתים אינם יודעים מאומה, Vehametim Einam Yodim Meumah,
what does that mean? אלו רשעים. Elu Reshaim. So if the live
are the צדיקים, Tzaddikim, the dead are the רשעים Reshaim שבחייהם קרויים
מתים. Shebechayeihen Kruyim Meisim. They're like the walking dead. They're dead even
when they're alive. They're unaware of what life really means and about
the responsibility. They're going oblivious through life. שנאמר ואתה חלל רשע נשיא
ישראל. Shene'emar Ve'ata Chalal Rasha Nesi Yisrael. You are a corpse, you
corpse, you wicked person, prince of Israel. ואיבעית אימא מהכא על פי
שנים עדים או שלשה עדים יומת המת. Veiba'it Eima Me'hacha Al Pi
Shnayim Eidim O Shlosha Eidim Yummat Hamet. By two or three witnesses
will the dead die? חי הוא! Chay Hu! What do you mean
the dead die? He's not dead yet! But he's
alive! אלא המת מעיקרא. Ela Hamet Me'ikara. He's already dead even because
he's so wicked and he is oblivious of his responsibilities, it's as
if he's already dead. So, thank you. So the point being you
tried to prove from
that פסוק Posuk that the dead don't know. No, that's not what
the literal פסוק Posuk means. The literal פסוק Posuk means is that
the people that are wicked are oblivious and they walk through life
oblivious. The people that are actually dead, they might be aware about
what goes on in this world. I wonder if it's only if
they're dead and they're also צדיקים Tzaddikim so they still remain alive.
After that it doesn't tell us. But it is quite possible that
even those that are really dead are aware. And this is going
to be the continued theme of the גמרא. Gemara. We have no
proof. We have no proof. But you can't prove from that פסוק
Posuk otherwise. And now the גמרא Gemara is going to continue to
discuss that point.
So we're going to, yes,
it does seem to, I've thought about this a lot, but it
seems from this use of the word רשע Rasha here that we
really is a very broad, it's a very powerful term to mean
something very different than what we might assume. In other words, a
רשע Rasha here in this context means a person who goes through
life mindlessly. And as a result might be inclined to behave in
all sorts of ways. But it's not a narrow definition or application
to an evil person.
Exactly. I think you're right. I think it's a good point especially
as we move into אלול Elul and the whole discussion about צדיקים,
Tzaddikim, רשעים Reshaim and so on. It seems like if you say
here's the צדיקים, Tzaddikim, here's the רשעים, Reshaim, like where's everybody else?
Are you describing two ends? And you are right the simple sense
although the גמרא Gemara doesn't elaborate is that the exception here is
the צדיק. Tzaddik. The צדיקים, Tzaddikim, they are alive even after they
die. Everybody else is essentially broadly defined as רשע Rasha because they
go through life oblivious.
In other words, it requires working on a certain awareness of the
meaning of
your existence.
Thank you. That's a
very excellent point and in a way it also ties a little
bit into point I was making at the beginning about the רב's
Rav's idea of עונג, Oneg, that doing מצוות Mitzvot is a sort
of conscious affirmation of meaning of life and what it means to
go through life sort of in this almost oblivious state without that
sort of awareness and affirmation. Yes, thank you. So now the גמרא
Gemara is not done with this discussion whether the dead are aware
about what goes on in this world. Let's take a look the
first middle-sized line here on יח עמוד ב. Yud Chet Amud Bet.
בני רבי חייא נפקו לקריתא. Benai Rabbi Chiya Nafku Lekiryata. So the
sons of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya went out to the villages
to oversee their investments and their property. ואייקרו להו תלמודייהו. V'aikru Lehu
Talmudaihu. So their learning became literally heavy on them meaning they started
forgetting their learning because they were too involved in business.
הוו מצטערי לאדכורי. Havu Mitzta'ari Leadkurei. They were going to pains to
try to remember their learning. אמר ליה חד לחבריה. Amar Lei Chad
Lechavrei. So one said to his fellow, ידע אבון בהאי צערא. Yada
Abbon Behai Tza'ara. Our father is aware, our dead father is aware
of the pain we're suffering
in our struggling to remember our תורה. Torah. So he said, אמר
ליה אידך מנא ידע. Amar Lei Idach Minna Yada. How could he
know? והכתיב יכבדו בניו
ולא ידע. V'hachtiv Yichbedu Vanav Velo Yeda. His sons will be honored
and he will not know, but presumably there's a play on words
from יכבדו Yichbedu from כובד, Koved, will be weighed down, will be
sort of here, our learning has been sort of too heavy for
us, seems to be like it applies this פסוק Posuk directly and
the father won't know. He doesn't know what happened. אמר ליה אידך
ולא ידע. Amar Lei Idach Velo Yeda. You tell me he doesn't
know? והכתיב אך בשרו עליו יכאב ונפשו עליו תאבל. V'hachtiv Ach Besaro
Alav Yichav Venafsho Alav Te'eval. That his flesh will pain him, of
the dead person, and his soul will mourn him. So will mourn
for him. So ואמר רבי יצחק: V'amar Rabbi Yitzchak: קשה רימה למת,
kasha rima l'met, what does it mean his flesh will pain him?
That the
maggots when they eat away the flesh of a dead person כמחט
בבשר החי, k'machat bivsar hachai, like a needle, you know, poking into
a live person's flesh. So they're aware, they suffer when they're—the body
decomposes—so the dead are aware of
what's happening. אמרי: Amri: says back, בצער דידהו ידעי, b'tzara d'idhu yad'ei,
yes, they know the afflictions that are occurring to them, with what's
happening to their body they're aware of, but בצער דאחרינא, b'tzara d'achrina,
the things that are happening, the pains that are happening to other
people, לא ידעי, lo yad'ei, they're not aware of.
So again, maybe he knows, maybe he doesn't.
Right, right. But that's a good point, meaning we haven't proven they
don't, but sort of you're right, the default assumption is if you
want to tell me the dead knows something, you have to prove
it. The assumption is the dead don't know anything, they're dead. That's
a good point. If you can't prove it, it's not happening.
So okay, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, ולא ידע? v'lo yada?
Is it that the dead not know? והתניא: V'hatanya: מעשה בחסיד אחד,
Maaseh b'chasid echad, this famous story, a story of a certain righteous
person שנתן דינר לעני. shenatan dinar l'ani. He gave a דינר, dinar,
which is a serious amount of money, like a $20 bill, to
an
עני ani בערב ראש השנה b'erev Rosh Hashanah ובשני בצורת, uv'shnei batzoret,
and it was a time of famine where money was not so
easy to come by. והקניטתו אשתו, V'hiknitatu ishto, and his wife got
very angry at him that he gave that type of money to
an עני. ani. והלך ולן בבית הקברות, V'halach v'lan b'veit hakevarot, so
he basically she kicked him out of the house, so he went
and he slept that night in the cemetery. This is ערב ראש
השנה, erev Rosh Hashanah, so it's the night of ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah presumably. ושמע שתי רוחות שמספרות זו לזו. V'shama shtei ruchot shemesaprot
zu l'zu.
He heard two spirits speaking to one another. אמרה חדא לחברתה, Amra
chada l'chavertah, one said to her friend, two female spirits, חברתי, chaverti,
my friend, בואי ונשוט בעולם, bo'i v'nashut ba'olam, let's go float around
in the world, fly around in the world, ונשמע מאחורי הפרגוד מה
פורענות בא לעולם, v'nishma m'achorei haparoged mah puranut ba l'olam, and we
will hear from behind the curtain, somehow the curtain that divides, you
know, God and the heavenly retinue or the rest of the world,
anyway where the secrets are discussed behind the curtain, we will hear
from there what afflictions will come to the world this coming year.
Interesting, they're going to—what about the good things? But okay, somehow maybe
they're interested in the afflictions. So let's hear what the bad stuff
that will happen to this world, that will happen to the world
in the coming year, because presumably this is on ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah, this is when things get decided. So let's hear what's going
to be decided for this coming year. אמרה לה חברתה, Amra lah
chavertah, so the friend spirit said to her, איני יכולה, aini yecholah,
I can't, כי קבורה אני במחצלת של קנים. ki kvurah ani b'machtzelet
shel kanim. I am buried in a mat of reeds. Now what
exactly a mat of reeds presents the spirit from floating is not
exactly clear. We'll see later it could be some, you know, magical
assumption that somehow that binds the body or binds the spirit, I
have no idea why. But we will see later that that was
actually an embarrassment to be buried in this mat of reeds.
It might have been referring to a time we'll see in the
גמרא Gemara that at a later—at a certain stage, you know, they
established that all the dead should be buried in simple shrouds. At
an earlier stage, people spent a lot of money on the coffins,
on the ways in which the dead were clothed. So this person
is being buried in a mat of reeds, presumably she was buried
in almost like a pauper's grave, in a very simple—she's poor, right,
exactly. And maybe somehow because she wasn't buried in enough—in an appropriate
way—she is not—her spirit is not free. Okay, so there seems to
be some type of a message like that, which also is a
message of you have to take care of how you bury the
dead or somehow their spirit remains bound. Seems it could be a
possible sub—you know, subtextual not so subtextual message. So let's take a
look. אלא לכי את ושוטו, Ela l'chi at v'shutu, you go, you
fly, ומה שאת שומעת אמרי לי, umah she'at shoma'at imri li, and
you tell me what you hear. הלכה היא, Halcha hi, so she
went, ושטה, v'shata, she flew, she flew, ובאה ואמרה לה, uva'ah v'amrah
lah, and she came back and she told her חברתה, chavertah, and
her friend told her, חברתי, chaverti, my friend, מה שמעת מאחורי הפרגוד?
mah shamat m'achorei haparoged? What did you hear from behind the curtain?
אמרה לה, Amra lah, she said to her, שמעתי שכל הזורע ברביעה
ראשונה. shamati shekol hazore'a b'revi'ah rishonah. I heard anybody who plants in
the first rains because they would be—there would be identified three times
in the year basically in חשוון Cheshvan of an early rain, a
middle rain, and a late rain. So whoever plants
in the first rain, ברד מלקה אותו. barad malkeh oto. So that
rain, that stuff will be harder—there's going to be a hail—and the
stuff planted early will be harder when the hail comes, and it'll
be broken by the hail.
אזל הוא, Azal hu, so he said, "Oh, that's good advice." So
he went, וזרע ברביעה שניה, v'zara b'revi'ah shniyah, and he planted in
the second rain. So then when the hail came, his was more
sort of flexible, his stuff hadn't hardened as much. שכל עולם
כולו לקה, Shekol olam kulo lakah, everybody else's grain was smitten, שלו
לא לקה, shelo lo lakah, his wasn't. Now here he's a חסיד,
chasid, but he's not telling anybody else what he heard. So you
wonder about that because it wouldn't affect him, it's not like other
times where like a win—you know, this could be a win-win situation.
Reminds me of what they say, you know, about Napoleon had—not Napoleon,
what's his name? Rothschild, how he made his money in the Napoleonic
wars. You know this? He had these carrier pigeons, so he had
like—he had earlier information about the... who had won the battles or
not. What? Secure message. Secure message. So he had inside information, so
he found out early, I think, that Napoleon had like won, but
rather than buy, he started selling on the stock market. And everybody
knew he had this information, so everybody else sold, and then he
picked it all up at dirt cheap prices. So that would be
like a win-lose, you know, but this could have been a win-win.
I don't know why he didn't tell anybody else.
Who was he going to tell people? What was he going to
tell people?
Maybe nobody would have believed him, you mean. All right.
Well, maybe his crops would be more valuable.
Oh, that's true too. Yeah.
Where did this spirit learn this from?
There were some, you know, the heavenly tribunal somewhere up in heaven
when they were deciding what was going to happen to the world
on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, these things were being discussed and whispered
and they were happening behind the curtain. We don't know exactly. But
some type of, you know, discussion behind this curtain that is where
the private things for the world get discussed. Exactly. Yes.
I have a different question. How did the spirit know?
Well, the story isn't over. We're going to hear about the rest
of this
over the course of a year of famine. Yes, in the הלכתא
hilcheta that we have about response to famine, it would be stronger.
Right, that's what David says.
Right, oh, combined with David's point, it's a year of famine, right.
So, right, it's not very pious, right. Okay. Anyway, so okay,
anyway, let's take a look. So that's what he did. Now, the
story isn't over. לשנה אחרת הלך ולן בבית הקברות. leshana acheret halach
velan beveit hakevarot. Next year he said, you know, if it's good
one year, it'll be good the next year. So he went and
he took a sleep, he went to sleep in the cemetery again.
Without his wife.
Without his wife, could you imagine? ושמע אותן שתי רוחות שמספרות זו
עם זו. veshama otan shtei ruchot shemesaperot zo im zo. He heard
the same spirits. אמר חדא לחברתה, amar chada lachaverta, בואי ונשוט בעולם
ונשמע מאחורי הפרגוד מה פורענות בא לעולם. boi venashut baolam venishma meachorei
hapargod ma puranut ba laolam.
So she said to her friend, let's go fly around the world
and find out what's going to happen in the
world. אמרה לה חברתה. amra la chaverta. By the way, it's also
funny that they're flying around the world, but they're hearing from behind
the curtain. Like flying around the world seems to be like, right,
they're looking down here. But you imagine going to the curtain is
flying, anyway. Anyway, אמרה לה חברתה, amra la chaverta, לא כך אמרתי
לך? lo kach amarti lach? Haven't I already told you? איני יכולה,
eini yechola, שאני קבורה במחצלת של קנים. sheani kevura bemachatzel shel kanim.
I can't because I'm in this mat of reeds. אלא לכי את,
ela lechi at, ומה שאת שומעת בואי ואמרי לי. uma sheat shomaat
boi veimri li. You, whatever you hear, you come tell me. הלכה
ושטה, halcha veshata, she flew, ובאה ואמרה לה. uvaa veamra la. She
said to her חברתה. chaverta. אמר לה חברתה, amar la chaverta, then
her friend said to her, חברתי מה שמעת מאחורי הפרגוד? chaverti ma
shamat meachorei hapargod?
What did you hear from behind the curtain? אמרה לה, amra la,
she said to her, שמעתי שכל הזורע ברביעה שניה שדפון מלקה אותו.
shamati shekol hazoreia berevia shnia shidafon malka oto.
Anybody that plants in the second
planting, this
harsh wind will smite it. But if you do it early in
the first planting, then it'll be stiff enough that it won't be
affected by this wind. הלך וזרע ברביעה ראשונה, halach vezara berevia rishona,
so he planted in the first rain. שכל העולם כולו נשדף, shekol
haolam kulo nishdaf, everybody else's was smitten, ושל אותו לא נשדף, veshel
oto lo nishdaf, his was not. אמרה לו אשתו, amra lo ishto,
מפני מה אשתקד, mipnei ma eshtakad, why last year, שכל העולם כולו
לקה ושלך לא לקה? shekol haolam kulo laka veshelcha lo laka? Last
year you decided you were going to plant in the second rain
and it happened and it worked out perfectly. Everybody's got smitten, you
didn't. ועכשיו שכל העולם כולו נשדף ושלך לא נשדף? veachshav shekol haolam
kulo nishdaf veshelcha lo nishdaf? And this year you also lucked out,
but you planted in the first rain. You obviously have some inside
track. How did you know what to be doing? סח לה כל
הדברים הללו. sach la kol hadevarim halalu. So
he told her the whole story about the spirits. Okay, so that's
how we know too. אמרו לא היו ימים מועטים, amru lo hayu
yamim muatim,
there was not too many days, meaning soon afterward, עד שנפלה קטטה
בין אשתו של אותו חסיד, ad shenafela ktata bein ishto shel oto
chasid,
between the wife of that חסיד, chasid, ובין אמה של אותה ריבה,
uvein ima shel ota riva, and the mother of that girl that
was buried in the mat of reeds, that they were, that they
had some fight. אמרה לה, amra la, so the wife of this
חסיד chasid said to the mother of this girl, לכי ואראך בתך
שקבורה במחצלת של קנים. lechi veareich bitech shekevura bemachatzel shel kanim. She
said like as a way of sort of attacking her, said, ha,
your daughter is buried in a mat of reeds! Come, I'll show
you she's buried in a mat of reeds, which apparently would have
been a matter of public shame. Although it's interesting it says let
me show you, not I'm going to tell people, which might mean
that the mother herself wasn't aware of how her daughter was buried.
Anyway, but somehow the point was hurting her feelings. Right. Well, the
wife of the חסיד, chasid, we see, wasn't such a חסידה chasida
because she was the one that got angry that he gave a
דינר dinar to the עני, ani, right? So she's not coming off
too good in this story. Okay, but it is a little bit
unclear whether the mother of this daughter... No, no, but she said
this to... oh, the second year she didn't kick him out of
the house. Oh, I see. Oh, that's a good point. I see,
because then they had made some money after that. Okay. Anyway, לשנה
אחרת. leshana acheret. Okay, fine. That was their fight. לשנה אחרת הלך
ולן בבית הקברות. leshana acheret halach velan beveit hakevarot. And he said,
good for two years, good for the third. Went and he slept
in the cemetery. ושמע אותן רוחות שמספרות זו עם זו. veshama otan
ruchot shemesaperot zo im zo. He heard the spirits speaking to one
another. אמרה לה חברתה, amra la chaverta, so one said to the
other, חברתי בואי ונשוט בעולם ונשמע מאחורי הפרגוד מה פורענות בא לעולם.
chaverti boi venashut baolam venishma meachorei hapargod ma puranut ba laolam. Let's
fly around the world and find out from behind the curtain what
bad things are going to happen. אמרה לה חברתה, amra la chaverta,
הניחי לי. henichi li. She said to her, look, my friend, leave
me alone. דברים שביני לבינך, devarim shebeini leveinech, things that we have
been discussing between the two of us, נשמעו בין החיים, nishmeu bein
hachayim, have been heard amongst the living. Okay. Now, what I find
fascinating is the sense
you get is how she... heard amongst the living because what
was said to her mother, not the fact that
the חסיד *Chassid* said it to his wife, right?
So still do they hear everything or do they only hear things
that sound directly applied to them? Right, and that could be also.
And maybe that's why she didn't say I'm in a מחצלת של
קנים *mechitzat shel kanim*, maybe her bones had been reburied, I don't
know. But it still doesn't prove they know everything that happened in
the world. Maybe again things that are directly relevant to them. Anyway,
let's take a look. אלמא ידעי alma yada’ei. *Alma yad'ei*, so you
see that they know what happened in the world, but again it's
not so clear because they didn't know until this second event. Anyway,
ודילמא *Vedilema*, no, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says not necessarily. ודילמא איניש
אחרינא שכיב ואזיל ואמר להו *Vedilema inish achreina shachiv ve'azil ve'amar lehu*.
Maybe somebody in the meantime had died and the word got around,
right? Because this guy was telling his wife,
so the word got around. So somebody had died and this person
who died, this spirit went up and he said let me tell
you what's been happening down there. So you don't know that they
directly heard, they might have heard from somebody who had been living
when this information was being shared and then went up and told
them. So all of this was a fascinating story to try to
prove whether the dead know what's happening. Yes.
What what are we really supposed to learn from this story?
Not me.
I'm open, but yes.
What what is this דילמא *dilema* that the dead communicate with one
another, that this man was alive, he knew the story because he
was alive during this time?
Yes, trying to prove that the dead are aware about what happened.
Meaning I don't think you could try to interpret this metaphorically, Rachel,
like you know I know you would like to, but I actually
do think that there was, you know, even nowadays, right, it's extremely
prevalent the belief that you know the dead are aware about what's
happening to us or what's happening in this world and people communicate
with the spirits of you know relatives who have passed away. This
is extremely popular, you know, common belief and it seems like the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was actually questioning that. Like the way my read
about it is that you know that it was certainly the common
belief that it was taken for granted and that the rabbis were
sort of questioning, maybe being a little skeptical and questioning is this
really true? Like is this just popular belief or is it really
true? And that that's what's what's really there is a question about
whether they whether this was true or not. I should say since
we mentioned אבילות *aveilus* that some people think that some of the
laws of אבילות *aveilus*, the difference between the first three days and
the seven days and so on, have to do with degrees to
which the soul stays around the corpse in the cemetery or further
departs up to heaven and so on. There really were a lot
of beliefs about this. Tali, did you want to say something?
שלמה המלך *Shlomo HaMelech* conjured up שמואל Shmuel's הנביא *Shmuel HaNavi*. Well
yes, and שמואל Shmuel.
*Shmuel* seemed to know what was going on.
Well that's true, it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just now
brings that as evidence. That is true.
But we're getting into this whole discussion because because
we were talking about having your ציצית tzitzit *tzitzit* out in front
of a dead person because we're talking about learning תורה *Torah* in
front of a dead person, right.
So I guess they had to make it seem like they're in
some I don't know.
Well look, I think it's worth mentioning. I don't think they had
to make it seem, as I said, I think that these are
very common even today beliefs and that were probably extremely prevalent in
the time of חז״ל *Chazal*. I mainly see חז״ל *Chazal* more as
sort of as being more skeptical than you know maybe the more
common beliefs would be. That's at least my view. You could say
the opposite. But I also see that when we have questions, for
example, like when we do certain things, I said for example the
observance of אנינות *aninut*, is it ללעוג למת *leloeg lamet*? And there's
this questions about observations of aspects of אבילות *aveilus*, הספד *hesped*, is
it for the כבוד *kavod* of the family or the כבוד *kavod*
of the מת meis *met*? Different aspects of אבילות *aveilus* are they
the כבוד *kavod* of the? What do you mean כבוד המת kavod
hames, *kavod hamet*? Do you mean כבוד המת *kavod hamet* like the
spirit is there and it needs to be honored and there's a
the spirit is feeling certain things and feeling dishonor? Or do we
interpret these issues like the dragging of the ציצית *tzitzit* that it's
not about what the spirits are thinking, but it's about sort of
the messages we are sending to ourselves and the honor that we
show and the respect that we show to those that were here
and you know and so on. I think that's the question of
how do we think about what honoring the dead means, you know,
are there spirits that are being honored or does it mean something
much more practical for us in this world? So that's why I
think it's really pushing on this question. But I do think it's
common to believe that no, there is a spirit that we are,
you know, when we're honoring the spirit of the dead person, I
think even nowadays people think things like that, yes.
Well certainly we've all been at celebrations where that has been promulgated
by rabbinic leadership. Shall we push a little further to express your
views on this subject? No. Okay. So moving on. I want more
to say. Yes.
I have a
friend
who's
a conservative rabbi, Lauren, and she has used this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
making to speaking on the cemetery as a comfort to people who
because this shows that the dead do have an awareness, especially the
mother with the daughter, that it could be I mean I know
that she has done this in an effective way that people should
feel that
their the dead do are somehow connected. Right.
Well, I think that reflects what, I think that reflects what David
said, that it is a very comforting belief that the dead are
not, you know, still are somewhat aware and present and present at
שמחות or, you know, and somewhat connected to what's going on. It
is an extremely comforting belief and if you believe in a if
you believe in a world of the spirit and an עולם הבא
olam haba which is not just, you know, when the sort of
the future messianic times but an עולם הבא olam haba where the
soul goes after death, it's also not a, you know, not much
of an extension of that, which is why I think it is
such a pervasive belief amongst all people, you know, this idea. The
question what I find surprising is not that the גמרא Gemara believes
it, but that the גמרא Gemara is actually questioning it, that the
גמרא Gemara is saying, you know, based on פסוקים psukim from קהלת,
Kohelet, which are some of the most rationalistic and sort of, you
know, types of פסוקים psukim that challenge the question of life as
of the meaning of life and the and, you know, and the
spirit and, you know, it says, you know, the animals die and
people die and all those types of things. I that's what I
find is is surprising, the skepticism. Yes.
There's the common belief of the converse as well, that the acts
by the living affect the souls of dead.
Right,
that's true as well. Right. Yeah. Right, exactly.
And you're doing it for the זכות zchus
of the נפטר niftar and all of those things.
Exactly, exactly. So I think that those are definitely, you know, the
most pervasive because they're very primal.
People want to feel that the departed are still close to them.
Right.
Absolutely. Absolutely. And that's whenever יזכור Yizkor is spoken... Exactly, exactly. And
they were saying, right. So that is, yeah. This connection, this is
some... Right. Right. That's why people go and visit cemeteries. And I
think that, you know, something is going on, right, feels better or
whatever that's a primal feeling. And going back to your point Rachel,
I think stories like this, they're so graphic and interesting, you know,
whatever, that they really drive home that message, you know, they make
you, oh my gosh, yes it's true they really know, look at
this story. Yeah.
Both
a confirmation and belief in the soul.
Well right, that's the real, right. Right. Oh and right, that's the
point. Once you believe in a world of in a in a
soul who that transcends, you know, the physical existence, right, so then
this whole sense of a world of souls and so on if
you believe in a... exactly, it's exactly that. Okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara can let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues.
It says like this, תא שמע, tasha, we're not done. We're trying
to still prove whether they know or not. זעירי הוה מפקד זוזי
גבי אושפיזכתיה, Zeiri hava mafkid zuzei gabei ushpizchtei, that זעירי Zeiri left
money by his innkeeper for safe keeping. עד דאזל ואתי מבי רב
ad d'azil v'atei mibei rav שכיבא, shichiva, from the time it took
him to go to רב's Rav house, you know, to learn in
the ישיבה Yeshiva רב Rav and to come back, his innkeeper died.
So he now he's gotta get his money back. So אזל בתרה
לחצר מות, azul basra lachatzar mavet, so he followed her body into
or maybe she'd already been buried,
anyway, into the into the cemetery of this of this woman innkeeper.
אמר לה, amar lah, he said to her, where he said at
the grave site, whatever, זוזי היכא, zuzei heicha, where are my where's
my money? אמרה ליה, amra lei, she said to him, דשקלינהו מתותי
צינורא דדשא בדוך פלן. d'shkalinhu mitutai b'tzinnora d'dasha b'duch plon.
So she said, by the way, go take it from under from
underneath this like whatever like a drainpipe or not drainpipe, צינורא דדשא,
tzinnora d'dasha, excuse me, right, a thing for what's it called for
the door, a hinge, a door hinge, right, in such and such
a place. That's where it is. It's under a door hinge in
such and such a place. ואימא לה לאמא, v'eima lah l'ima, and
by the way, as long as you're going back, while you're at
it, drop by the store, תשדרי לי מסרקי וגובתאי דכחלא, tishadli mishrai
v'gubtai d'kuchla, to send into my put into my into my coffin
or into my grave my haircomb and my eye shadow applicator. Right.
okay. You want to look your best. You never know when someone's
going to drop by. Yeah.
Yeah. Now, how is she going to bring it to me? I'm
already dead. So here's how she's going to bring it to me.
So send it to me בהדי פלוניתא דאתיא למחר bahadi plonita d'atya
l'machar together with so-and-so who's about to die tomorrow. So we already
found out that the way you get messages off is by somebody
who's about to go into the next world, right, that was the
answer before. So this person will die, but now by the way
I should say that there's a whole discussion in in מסכת שמחות,
Masechet Smachot, you know, there used to it talks against the practice
of throwing personal articles into the grave, which seemed to be a
very sort of common practice and again has to do with this,
you know, raises questions, I mean to one hand it's about sort
of a sense of loss and you put the most personal things
in and that you know there could be an aspect in which
it's helpful for the living in some types of grieving process but
obviously you know it also taps into this idea about where are
they going in the afterlife that they're going to be needing these
things.
The old Egyptian...
the old Egyptian idea, exactly. Exactly and all those little, right, all
those objects they put into the pyramid. So anyway, so here it’s
not surprising once we’re dealing with all of this about what dead
know and so on, that you’re having and you’re having come up
this idea of putting these personal items in with the dead. Yes.
This is a mocking story, the tone is of course, I mean
the tone of
the, I mean
it cannot, it cannot be taken seriously. Right.
I
again, I think that so much in the eyes of the reader
and the interpreter. I mean you could be right. For us it
might seem that way. I’m not so sure that that’s the intention.
Yes.
Well that’s what I
was just gonna say.
You think so? There’s no הלכה halacha here. It seems so.
What is רש״י Rashi thinking? But look, it’s mocking if it was
extremely common practice to throw personal items in with the grave, right?
Then having a dead person say where, you didn’t, I need my
personal items, you didn’t send them in with me, is no more
mocking than saying this person was buried in a mat of reeds,
the right things weren’t done for this dead person and they, you
know, for this מת and they need it. But the גמרא’s Gemara.
saying there’s no proof.
This is, well we’re trying to show proof.
You see she knows who’s going to die. That’s proof. So you
see, that’s where the גמרא Gemara is going with it.
This story is so much less than the previous one, really it
has that the dead spirits have a connection to God, they can
know what’s going on out there. Right, this is that they’re concerned
much more with.
If we say that someone should
be a מליץ יושר, maleitz yosher, so somehow we can attend our
spiritual needs through our dead.
This one’s totally, it’s nonsense.
Right,
it trivializes their concerns.
All right, I hear it that way.
Look, a human being, the living, have direct access to what other
people are going to do, but we don’t understand what God is
going to do. This story is constructed around more direct access between
the dead and what God is going to do, and the question
is whether they’re connected to what the living are going to do.
Right, but their point is that the second story is not about
them knowing God, it’s about their concern about very trivial issues. Right.
Well but they have, I understand, they have in other words it’s
constructed around having access.
Right, you mean but they do know who’s going to die. Right,
they do know who’s going to die. They can’t get their own
eyeshadow.
Yeah
as David said.
Yeah to put
all these little, what were they called? There was a word for
them, those little funerary items, anyway those little household items in with,
right.
That Pharaoh would need in the
afterlife.
Right. Exactly. All right so let’s see where this story goes. Yes.
But I wouldn’t say it trivializes it, not only the fact that
the cosmetic industry has always been a major industry, but also that
we know that the dead don’t eat or drink. Right. But there’s
a sense here of a living ongoing life where you care about
how you look. I wouldn’t dismiss it so quickly as mocking. Yeah,
interesting. Okay. So, the person looked like hell. All right.
All right so now the גמרא Gemara, says אלמא ידעי.
So you see they know what’s happening
because they know who’s going to die. They know who’s going to
die. So the גמרא Gemara says דילמא דומה קדים ומכריז. dilma duma
kadmim machrizum. Maybe Dumah who was the angel who was involved in
announcing who would die, he was, he had already made the announcement
up in heaven about who’s who’s going to be dying tomorrow, who’s
coming tomorrow. So therefore they don’t know because they know what’s happening
down here, they know because they got report about it up in
heaven. By the way, it assumes that if they know what’s happening
down here they know better than we know because they know who’s
going to die tomorrow, but then in the end it says no,
maybe they only know because that’s a special message that’s given up
in heaven. Who’s Dumah? He’s Dumah’s that angel. You look at רש״י,
Rashi, he says מלאך שהוא ממונה על המתים. malach shehu memuneh al
hamesim. Okay? Some type of angel over the dead, he knows. All
right. The name appears in תהלים Tehillim I think. Oh yeah? Ha!
In that sense. לא כל יורדי דומה. lo kol yordei duma. Dumah.
Yeah so that’s true but to turn it into the giving personal
names to angels only occurs in the Book of Daniel and it
only occurs as the ירושלמי Yerushalmi said they were names that they
took with them from בבל, Bavel, that basically was a Persian practice
to give personal names to angels, until then there was never personal
names. So Dumah you’re right is a sense of the, of like
שאול, Sheol, the underworld, but to make it into a personalized angel
is the גמרא. Gemara By the way this entire סוגיא sugya of
the dead is in a Zoroastrian context. Right. What makes you think
it’s Zoroastrian? No in other words the religious context, this whole thing
is emerging from בבל. Bavel. Right, right. Assyria is all of it
is right is right. He shared this picture. Yes please. Yes I
see that’s an eyeshadow applicator.
And you have
a reference to עתיק יומין Atik Yomin which is also from בבל.
Bavel. Right. עתיק יומין Atik Yomin was referred to God as עתיק
יומין. Atik Yomin. Right, that’s right. That’s unusual. Yeah that’s a good
point. Yeah yeah yeah.
Yeah yeah yeah.
That’s a very good point, you’re right.
But in terms of where this comes from I don’t
know because it’s אבות דרבי נתן Avos de-Rabbi Noson so I’m not
sure if it’s ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you know based, I don’t
know for sure, at least the first story. Anyway so let’s see
where this story goes. Yes. Let's go, let's go a bit further.
גמרא Gemara's says like this: So, okay, maybe דומה. Duma. תא שמע:
Ta Shma: דאבוה דשמואל הוה קמפקיד גביה זוזי דיתמי. De'avuhu Dishmuel hava
kamafkid gabei zuzei deyatmi. So שמואל Shmuel father, who appears a number
of times in the גמרא, Gemara had the money of orphans kept
by him. He was the one that was safe keeping them.
כי נח נפשיה, Ki nach nafshei, so he died, the father of
שמואל. Shmuel לא הוה שמואל גביה. Lo hava Shmuel gabei. שמואל Shmuel
wasn't there; presumably
if שמואל Shmuel was there, he would have made sure
to have told שמואל Shmuel on his deathbed, you know, this important
information
about where he
was keeping other people's money.
הוה קקרו ליה, Hava ka karu lei, so people were starting to
call שמואל Shmuel,
בר אכיל
זוזי דיתמי,
bar
achil
zuzei deyatmi, the son of the person that eats, like steals, consumes
the money of orphans.
So he was getting a bad reputation, his father's getting a bad
reputation. אזל אבתריה לחצר מות,
Azal abatarei
l'vei
chasat mavet, so שמואל Shmuel, went to the graveside. אמר להו, Amar
lehu, so he said to
him, or he said to them, to the spirits that were hovering
around the cemetery, בעינא אבא, Ba'ina Aba, I need אבא. Aba. So,
אבא, Aba, because that was his name, אבוה דשמואל Avuhu deShmuel's personal
name actually was אבא. Aba. But they were somewhat, they were a
little bit mocking him and they interpreted it as "I want dad".
אמרו ליה, Amru lei, they said to him, אבא טובא איכא הכא,
Aba tuba ika hacha, we have a lot of אבא Abas buried
in this cemetery. אמר להו, Amar lehu, so he said okay, בעינא
אבא בר אבא. ba'ina Aba bar Aba. Apparently his grandfather's name was
also אבא. Aba. I want אבא Aba the son of אבא. Aba.
אמרו ליה, Amru lei, they said to him, אבא בר אבא נמי
איכא טובא, Aba bar Aba nami ika tuba, we also have a
lot of אבא Abas who are sons of אבא Abas in it,
so again they were mocking him. הכא אמר להו, hacha amar lehu,
fine, בעינא אבא בר אבא אבוה דשמואל. ba'ina Aba bar Aba Avuhu
deShmuel. I want אבא Aba the son of אבא Aba the father
of שמואל, Shmuel making clear I want my father, I want us.
היכא היכא, Heicha, heicha, where is he? אמרו ליה, Amru lei, סליק
למתיבתא דרקיעא. salik l'metivta derakiya. So talking about the life of the
spirits afterwards and here's the link context into the sort of the
cosmetic concerns. He went up to the ישיבה Yeshiva up in heaven.
אדהכי, Adahachi, חזייה ללוי דיתיב אבראי. chazya l'Levi deyativ abarayi. So as,
so he was, so his father wasn't coming about, his father was
too busy up in the ישיבה Yeshiva in heaven, but he saw
לוי, Levi, also the spirit of לוי, Levi, who was sitting outside
of this little group of spirits in the cemetery. אמר ליה, Amar
lei, אמאי יתיב אבראי, amai yativ abarayi, why are you sitting on
the outside of the group? מאי טעמא לא סלקת, Mai ta'ama lo
salakt, why have you not gone up, presumably to the heavenly ישיבה
Yeshiva where my father is? אמר ליה, Amar lei, so לוי Levi
said to שמואל, Shmuel. דאמרי לי כל הני שני דלא סלקת למתיבתא
דרבי אפס, de'amri li kol hanei shani d'lo salikt l'metivta deRabbi Afis,
all those years that you did not go to the ישיבה Yeshiva
of רבי אפס, Rabbi Afis, which is alluding to a different story
where he stayed out of רבי אפס Rabbi Afis's ישיבה, Yeshiva, ואחלשתיה
לדעתיה, v'achlishteih l'daiteih, and you made him feel sort of, you know,
did not disappoint him but made him literally weakened his, what's the
word here, you disturbed him, right, you anguished him with not having
gone to his ישיבה, Yeshiva, לא מעלינן לך למתיבתא דרקיעא. lo ma'alinan
lach l'metivta derakiya. So those years you stayed out of רבי אפס
Rabbi Afis's ישיבה, Yeshiva, you're going to have to wait those number
of years before you're brought into the heavenly ישיבה Yeshiva up above.
So here you see that what the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim do
after their death is they are learning up in the heavenly ישיבה.
Yeshiva. אדהכי והכי, Adahachi vahachi, so while he was having this conversation
with לוי, Levi, אתא אבא. ata Abba. So his father maybe got
a little time off from the ישיבה Yeshiva up above and came
down to speak to him. חזייה דהוה קבכי ואחיך. Chazya d'hava k'bachi
v'achichi. So he saw his father was crying and laughing. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so שמואל Shmuel's said to his father, מאי טעמא קבכית,
mai ta'ama k'bachit, why are you crying? אמר ליה, Amar lei, דלעגלא
d'la'agya soon, like we say in קדיש, Kaddish, it's pretty means quickly,
soon קא אתית, ka'atit, you'll be coming in the set, you'll be
dying. מאי טעמא קאחיכת, mai ta'ama k'achichat, so why are you laughing?
דחשיבת בהאי עלמא טובא, Dechashivat b'hai alma tuba, because you have such
great status in this world, in the afterlife. So although you'll be
dying, you've achieved greatly and you'll be given great honor in this
world in the afterlife. אמר ליה, Amar lei, one wonders by the
way why it took him so long in his little, you know,
when the dead were mocking him, till he finally said my father,
אבוה דשמואל. Avuhu deShmuel. Was he avoiding mentioning his name not to
associate it, you know, with the dead? And after then he mentions
his name, we find out that he soon going to be joining
his father, you know, so I wonder if there was some, something
about that in the story. Anyway, אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he
finally gets around to saying to him, אי חשיבנא נעיילו ללוי. i
chashivna, ne'alu l'Levi. So if I'm so important, so for my sake
they should have לוי, Levi, have him come into the ישיבה. Yeshiva.
ועיילו ללוי, V'ailu l'Levi, so fine, they brought לוי Levi up in
for the sake of שמואל. Shmuel So it's very nice even at
this moment he hears about his impending death and all these concerns
about is לוי, Levi, the לוי Levi who's already dead. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, זוזי דיתמי היכא, zuzei deyatmi heicha, so then he gets
down to business, where is the money of the orphans? אמר ליה,
Amar lei, זיל שקלינהו באנצא דריחייא, zil shaklinhu b'atza derichaya, you go
take them, they're in the, the sort of like the the hold,
the that they use for the for the for the millstone. עילאי
ותתאי דידן, Ila'ei v'tata'ei didan, so apparently there was money on the
top and in the bottom, that belongs to us, ומציעאי דיתמי, umitzi'ei
deyatmi, the money in the middle, the orphans'. אמר ליה איגנובי גנבי
Amar lei ignuvei ganvei if stuff gets stolen נגנבו מדידן nignavu mi-didan
they'll steal our money first although I don't know why they don't
maybe they're buried a little bit deeper. אי אכלה ארעא Ei achla
ara'a if it gets somehow consumed by the earth I don't know
how that would happen but anyway somehow if something would happen from
below אכלה מדידן achla mi-didan it would be our money first theirs
is most protected it's in the middle. So obviously you know in
response to those that say this father consumed the money of the
orphans here you see the great extent that the father did to
protect them. So the גמרא Gemara says anyway what do we see
at the end of this story that the father knows what's going
to happen. How does he know what's going to happen? That guy
he knows where the money is that he knew from beforehand. He
knows what's going to happen he knows what's happening because he knows
that שמואל's Shmuel's about to die. Okay so again why can't you
say that דומא Duma announced it? So apparently because שמואל Shmuel that
was only when she's going to die like the next day. In
the story of the young girls or the young women they were
going to die the next day but he says soon you'll be
dying so that doesn't get announced yet and still שמואל's Shmuel's father
knew it. So you see they know what's going to happen. So
the גמרא Gemara said no דילמא שאני שמואל כיון דחשיב קדמו ומכרזי
dilma shani Shmuel keivan de-chashiv kadmu u-machrezei maybe שמואל Shmuel. is so
important that he gets announced that he's going to be coming many
days before it happens so even not just one day before. פנו
מקום Panu makom make space שמואל's Shmuel going to be coming soon
make space in the ישיבה yeshiva I guess for שמואל. Shmuel Okay
so you see that again they don't necessarily know what's going to
happen only maybe special things that are happening to their own body
people are about to die they know but they don't necessarily know
broadly what's going to happen. So let's just wrap this up. ואף
רבי יוחנן הדר ביה Ve-af Rabbi Yochanan hadar bei even though with
all of this we have not proven they know what happens even
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan in the end who says why should I
bother with my ציצית they don't know what's going to happen even
he reversed himself. דאמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יוחנן De-amar
Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yochanan מנין שמתים מספרים זה עם
זה minayin she-meisim mesaperim zeh im zeh how do you know that
the dead speak to one another the dead spirits. שנאמר she-ne'emar the
פסוק pasuk says ויאמר ה' אליו זאת הארץ אשר נשבעתי לאברהם ליצחק
וליעקב לאמר Vayomer Hashem eilav zos ha-aretz asher nishbati le-Avraham le-Yitzchak u-le-Yaakov
leimor this is the land that I have sworn to אברהם יצחק
ויעקב Avraham Yitzchak u-Yaakov to say I will give it to your
children. You know הראיתיך בעיניך her'isicha be-einecha God says to משה Moshe
right before he dies I've shown it to you in your eyes
you know this is the land you're not going to go in
but here's the land that I am going to give. So מאי
לאמר mai leimor what does לאמר leimor mean because the חז"ל Chazal
usually understand לאמר leimor means to say to somebody else. Who's משה
Moshe going to say this to? So אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה
Amar Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu le-Moshe God says to משה Moshe אמור להם
emor lahem you're about to die you go tell אברהם יצחק ויעקב
Avraham Yitzchak u-Yaakov ששבועה שנשבעתי לכם she-shvu'ah she-nishbati lachem what I had
promised them קיימתיה לבניכם kiyamtiha le-vaneichem I have fulfilled it so you
can now report to them that you have seen in your own
eyes you can go back to אברהם יצחק ויעקב Avraham Yitzchak u-Yaakov
and tell and tell them what has happened. Why wouldn't they know
without him? Okay so the גמרא's Gemara going to get to that.
אי סלקא דעתך דלא ידעי Ei salka da'atach de-la yad'ei כי אמרו
להו מאי הוה ki amru lehu mai hava so if they don't
know what's happening so so what if he tells them? Now of
course this is a different story because until now what was the
question the question was do they have direct access to information happening
here? Here it seems like the question is like are they even
conscious afterwards is there this sense of these conscious spirits because here
right רש"י Rashi says what's the question if אינם מבינים כלום אלא
צערא דגופא einam mevinim klum ela tza'ara de-gufa if they only know
the pain of their body which remember that was a whole discussion
about the רמה rimah maggots what good does it do to tell
them what's happened it must be that they're more aware but that
wasn't our question we had been assuming they were aware but remember
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan had originally said אין המתים יודעים מאומה ein
ha-meisim yode'im me'umah which is really means that they not just they
don't have access to the world they're not conscious beings at all
you know there's no awareness no consciousness. So you see there is
consciousness they talk with one another they're informed about what's going to
happen. So again it's sort of shifting he's not fully. I know
that was sort of taken for granted in all these stories but
apparently for רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan it wasn't taken for granted. So
anyway so the גמרא Gemara let's just finish this the גמרא Gemara
says like this אלא מאי דידעי ela mai de-yad'ei so what they
do know what's happening again shifting to not only they know what
משה's Moshe's going to tell them but they know they're conscious but
they know what's happening directly in this world so למה ליה למימר
להו lamah leih le-meimar lehu so why does משה Moshe have to
tell them? They'll know what's happening. So לאחזוקי לטיבותא למשה le-achzukei le-tivuta
le-Moshe so in order that they should be able to sort of
give gratitude to משה Moshe because he was the one that told
them and he was the one that made it happen so he's
coming to tell them look I you know they have gotten it
I have taken them out of מצרים Mitzrayim you know whatever made
it happen. But again it is interesting because it really makes it
clear that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was making a very extreme statement
not just they're not aware what's happening down here but maybe they're
like don't have any conscious existence at all. It also undercuts the
popular concept of the intimacy between the dead and the God because
because משה Moshe is the one that has to tell them what
does הקדוש ברוך הוא. Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu. Well no but that the
גמרא answers because you know that they should sort of recognize משה's
Moshe's contribution to that process. So you don't buy the answer. Let's
let's finish to the two dots just two more minutes אמר רבי
יצחק כל המספר אחרי המת כאלו מספר אחרי האבן Amar Rabbi Yitzchak
kol ha-mesaper acharei ha-mes ke-ilu mesaper acharei ha-even so here's seeming to
echo the first position of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan if you talk
about the dead it's like you're talking you know about a stone.
איכא דאמרי Ika de-amri some say דלא ידעי. de-la yad'ei. that they're
not aware at all what you're saying about them. ואיכא דאמרי, ve'ika
d'amri, דידעי ולא איכפת להו. d'yadi velo ichpas lehu. No, they are
aware, but they don't care, they're dead. So, but again, what that
says about things about כבוד המת, you know, and about don't talk
ill of the dead, right, it's again, who is that for? Is
that for the dead or is that for us? Now that I
think is part of what's going on here. Is that really true?
אמר רב פפא: Amar Rav Pappa: חדא שתין מלתא בתר דמר שמואל,
chada shtin milta batar demar Shmuel, ונפק קניא מצללא venafak kanya mitlala
ובזע לארנקא דמוחי. u'vaza l'arnaka d'mochi. So here's שמואל Shmuel again. Somebody
said bad things after שמואל Shmuel had passed away. They have no
reluctance talking about שמואל's Shmuel father, about שמואל Shmuel when he's dead,
you know, even though these are great sages. Anyway, somebody was saying
something bad about שמואל Shmuel after he passed away and a beam
from the roof fell and split his brain pan, split his head
in two. So you see that it's not that they don't care.
So the גמרא says, no. שאני צורבא מרבנן. shani tzurba m'rabanan. No,
a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham is different. דקודשא בריך הוא תבע ביקריה.
de'Kudsha Brich Hu tavei biy'karei. God is defending their honor. It's not
that the dead know, but God is defending how תלמידי חכמים talmidei
chachamim are spoken about in this world, which again gets to the
question: is it about the messages we send ourselves and what we
communicate to ourselves or is it what the dead are feeling? So,
אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי: Amar Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi: כל המספר
אחרי מיטתן של תלמידי חכמים נופל בגיהנום. kol hamesaper acharei mitatan shel
talmidei chachamim nofel b'Gehennom. Anybody that speaks after the מיטה, mita, now
that could mean the bed, like maybe their marital life, but it
actually seems from later it's not that, but it has to do
more with like, you know, the actions of the dead, of the
תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, falls into גיהנום. Gehennom. שנאמר: Shene'emar: והמטים עקלקלותם
יוליכם ה' את פועלי האוון שלום על ישראל. vehamatim akalkalotam yolichem Hashem
es po'alei ha'aven shalom al Yisrael. And the והמטים, hamatim, those that
lean or, you know, weigh their actions or whatever, you're weighing whether
somebody has done something like in a scale, right or wrong, so
if it is like perverse, if you make it perverse or claim
that it's perverse, יוליכם ה' את פועלי האוון שלום על ישראל, yolichem
Hashem es po'alei ha'aven shalom al Yisrael, God will lead those doers
of sin, peace to Israel. What's שלום על ישראל? shalom al Yisrael?
אפילו בשעה ששלום על ישראל, afilu besha'a sheshalom al Yisrael, even when
there's peace to Israel, like even maybe at the time of death
when it's already a time of שלום, shalom, of peace, nevertheless, יוליכם
ה' את פועלי האוון, yolichem Hashem es po'alei ha'aven, these sinners that
speak bad about תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, they'll go to גיהנום, Gehennom,
which obviously is tying into the discussions about שמואל Shmuel and שמואל's
father. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל: Tana d'vei Rabi Yishmael: אם ראית תלמיד
חכם שעבר עבירה בלילה אל תהרהר אחריו ביום. im ra'ita talmid chacham
she'avar aveira balayla al teharher acharav bayom. Again talking about respect of
תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, now it's even live תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim,
like the previous one. If you see a Torah sage that did
a sin during the day—and we're not claiming he did, he doesn't,
you know, sages sin too—but at least we can assume that, you
know, don't think that by the day, you know, he did a
sin at night, don't think that by the day, you know, he's
still the same bad things you were thinking last night. Why? שמא
עשה תשובה. shema asa teshuva. Because maybe he did תשובה. teshuva. If
it's a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, you can give him the benefit
of the doubt. So the גמרא says, give everyone the benefit? Well,
yes. So the גמרא says, anyway, so yes, that's a good point.
שמא סלקא דעתך? shema salka datcha? Maybe? אלא ודאי עשה תשובה. ela
vadai asa teshuva. No, he definitely did תשובה. teshuva. הני מילי hani
mili now, talking about how far this goes, בדברים שבגופו. bidvarim shebegufo.
That's when it's things like about his body, meaning about maybe sins
between him and God. אבל בממונו, aval bemamono, if you saw him
maybe cheat somebody out of money, עד דמהדר למריה, ad d'mahadar l'marei,
don't start, you know, don't start giving him the benefit until you
see that he actually has reformed his actions. So Rachel raises a
good question: in general, when are you being דן לכף זכות? dan
l'chaf zechut? Normally דן לכף זכות dan l'chaf zechut is somebody does
an ambiguous action and you interpret it favorably. Here, somebody did something
that clearly was wrong and the question is what do we sort
of assume about that person, you know, afterwards, about what they're going
to do in the future. But I also think that the end
about difference between בגופו begufo and בממונו bemamono is important, and it's
also issues about like, about issues about דן לכף זכות dan l'chaf
zechut and לשון הרע lashon hara as well. Difference about how you're
supposed to think well of other people but also how you have
to protect yourself and your own interests. So somebody who does this
type of stuff, you might not want to go into business with
him, you know. So it's different that you say, oh, maybe he
did תשובה teshuva because he was מחלל שבת mechalel Shabbos or whatever
he was, but don't start going into business with him until you
see some obvious evidence about how he's reformed his ways. Yes, two
points on similar... yeah, I always assumed if I saw someone doing
something that I've been taught was wrong that the תלמיד חכם talmid
chacham who's doing that knows a היתר heter that I've never learned.
Well, that's the normal דן לכף זכות dan l'chaf zechut if there's
some ambiguous type of way of interpreting it, right, but there's not
always that ambiguity. That often goes to... how does our actions in
this world affect something in that world over there? Yes, is that
a reflection that we can have an effect? Oh, that goes back,
yeah, that goes back to the other point, right,
about our
actions
affecting
that
שמואל
asked
that
לוי
Levi
be
accepted.
Okay,
more
of
this
tomorrow,
but
moving
on
to
הלכה
halacha
issues.